JAMES MACIUKENAS, PH.D.

773-290-9947 | blueform@gmail.com www.linkedin.com/in/james-maciukenas

DESIGNER | DEVELOPER | INSTRUCTOR

SUMMARY

Designer and Developer (web and print) with experience as strategic member of academic leadership teams and strong background in User Experience Research, Design Thinking, Communication, and Training. Team player with ability to serve as catalyst for innovative solutions to digital and print communication challenges. Establish rapport and credibility with diverse groups from students to board members, from developers to endusers. Recognized for project management, analysis, and achieving goals. Solution-oriented by implementing constraint-based designed solutions that work.

- User Experience Research
- Project Management

- Design Strategy
- Iterative Development

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Adobe Creative Cloud (Indesign, Photoshop, Illustrator, Dreamweaver, Premiere, Audition, Acrobat); Canva (web-based design layout tool); Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint); Google Apps (Analytics, Docs, Sheets, Slides); HTML/HTML5/CSS/CSS3; Bootstrap; Wordpress Design and Development; Drupal; Web-based Digital Signage Development; FTP; MySQL; phpMyAdmin; cPanel; Blackboard Learn; Blackboard ULTRA; Canvas; Google Classroom; Mac + PC

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

DEPAUL UNIVERSITY, Chicago, IL

Information Services - Web Developer, Advancement 2019-Present

Web design and development for Advancement Office

Adjunct Instructor, 2019-Present

- Web Design Tools Workshop (in-classroom)
- Introduction to Human-Computer Interaction (online)

ILLINOIS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (IIT), Chicago, IL

2005-Present

Senior Web Development and Graphic Design Coordinator, 2011-2019

Integrated design thinking and UX research methods to deliver innovative and useful communication solutions for online and print audiences of College of Science (CoS).

- Designed and implemented web features using UX research, improving audience engagement with growth in unique pageviews year over year.
- Coordinated website development, training and maintenance, reducing technical support and downtime.
- Coordinated Content Management System transitions, managing stakeholder relationships for successful implementation.
- Conceived branding strategy building recognition for college with six unique departments with stakeholder audiences including prospective students, alumni, friends, and industry, which contributed to largest donation of over \$7 Million.

Adjunct Instructor (IIT), 2006-Present

 Developed curricula and taught graduate and undergraduate online and in-classroom courses in Web Design and Development, Document Design, Technical Communication, Publication Management, and Public Engagement for Scientists. Mentored student (Eric Galicia) on class project, resulting in winning Alan Alda's Flame Challenge. (2015)

Project and Communications Associate (IIT), 2007-2011

• Completed web, print, and branding projects for CoS to raise awareness with prospective student, peer, alumni, and industry audiences.

Department Coordinator (IIT), 2005-2007

2019-Present

• Assisted Lewis Department of Humanities faculty and students with office tasks and technology support to improve efficiency.

PART-TIME CONSULTING EXPERIENCE

NEWCITY COMMUNICATIONS, INC., Chicago, IL

2015-Present

Web Developer and Print Magazine Production

• Supported Wordpress websites, increasing responsiveness and reducing security issues. Designed and prepared *Newcity Magazine* for production.

BUSINESS COMMUNICATION QUARTERLY (BCQ), Chicago, IL

2006-2013

Editorial Assistant

Assisted in preparation of manuscripts for on-time production and publication of BCQ.

NON-PROFIT VOLUNTEERING

AYSO YOUTH SOCCER, Evanston, IL Web Developer/ Assistant Coach

2016-Present

PIVOT ARTS, Chicago, IL

2014-Present

Creative Director/ Web Developer

• Designed promotional material and increased web security for arts organization.

ORDINARY PEOPLE INTERNATIONAL (OPI), NFP, Chicago, IL

2011-Present

Web Developer/ Creative Director

Worked with non-profit organization, which assists underserved communities in Chicago.

EDUCATION

- Ph.D., Technical Communication, Illinois Institute of Technology (IIT), Chicago, IL Thesis: Toward Usability Guidelines for Single—Window Web Interfaces
- M.S., Technical Communication and Information Design, IIT, Chicago, IL
 Thesis: Toward a Digital Humanities Course: Open Source Software for Rapid Content Transition
- Graduate Certificate, Digital Technologies: Design Art Practice, Concordia University, Montreal, QC
- B.F.A., Industrial Design, University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, IL

AWARDS

- Service Award. IIT. (2017)
- Nominated for Staff Team Excellence Award. IIT. (2012-2013)
- Award of Excellence—Technical Art: Promotional and Informational Design. Society for Technical Communication, Chicago. Annual Communications Competition. (2009)
- Kudos Award. IIT. (2008)
- Dean's Excellence Award for Staff. IIT. (2008)
- Award of Excellence—Technical Art: Informational Materials Design. Society for Technical Communication, Chicago. Annual Communications Competition. (2008)
- Award of Merit—Technical Publications: Promotional Materials. Society for Technical Communication, Chicago. Annual Communications Competition. (2008)
- Teaching Assistantship, IIT. (2006-2008)
- Dean's Half-Tuition Scholarship. IIT. (2005-2006)
- Centre Interuniversitaire des Arts Médiatiques (CIAM) *Graduate Certificate Student Research Funding Award*, Concordia University, Montreal, Quebec. (2004-2005)
- Outstanding Senior Award, University of Illinois, Industrial Design program. (1992)

JAMES MACIUKENAS, PH.D.

773-290-9947 | blueform@gmail.com www.linkedin.com/in/james-maciukenas

ADDENDUM

PUBLICATIONS

- Maciukenas, J. (2013). Toward usability guidelines for single-window interfaces (doctoral dissertation). Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, IL.
- Maciukenas, J. (2011). Selecting and integrating photography. In Riley, K. & Mackiewicz, J. (Eds.), *Visual composing: Document design for print and digital media* (pp. 128-146). Upper Saddle River, NJ: Prentice Hall.
- Maciukenas, J. (2011). Editing photography. In Riley, K. & Mackiewicz, J. (Eds.),
 Visual composing: Document design for print and digital media (pp. 147-163). Upper Saddle River, NJ: Pearson.
- Maciukenas, J. (2011). Print objects. In Riley, K. & Mackiewicz, J. (Eds.), *Visual composing: Document design for print and digital media* (pp. 228-235). Upper Saddle River, NJ: Pearson.
- Riley, K., Davis, M., Cox, A. & Maciukenas, J. (2009). 'Ethics in the details': Communicating Engineering ethics via micro-insertion. *IEEE Transactions on Professional Communication*, 52(1), 95-108.
- Riley, K., Davis, M., Cox, A. & Maciukenas, J. (2007). "Ethics in the details': An NSF project to integrate ethics into the graduate Engineering curriculum." Proceedings of the 2007 International Professional Communication Conference, IEEE Professional Communication Society.
- Maciukenas, J. & Riley, K. (2007). "Toward a feature system for analyzing dynamic web interfaces." *Proceedings of the 2007 International Professional Communication Conference*, IEEE Professional Communication Society.
- Maciukenas, J. (2006). "Sketching a grand order: Sketching a link between conceptualizing and realizing internet structure," *Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on the Convergence of Technology and Professional Communication*, Saratoga Springs, NY, pp. 326-334.
- Tillmans, M., **Maciukenas, J.,** Mastarone, G. & Garnett, K. (2006). "Personal information managers in the time of desktop search," *Proceedings of the Society of Technical Communication 53rd Annual Conference*, Las Vegas, Nevada, pp. 159-164.

PRESENTATIONS

- Maciukenas, J. & Riley, K. "Toward a feature system for analyzing dynamic web interfaces," Presentation at IEEE IPCC, Seattle, Oct. 2007.
- Maciukenas, J. & Riley, K. "A featural analysis of collaborative and dynamic web interfaces." Poster Presentation at the Digital Humanities and Computer Science Colloquium, Chicago, Oct. 2007.
- Maciukenas, J. "Sketching a grand order: Sketching a link between conceptualizing and realizing internet structure," Poster Presentation at the IEEE Conference on the Convergence of Technology and Professional Communication, Saratoga Springs, NY, October 2006.

ADDENDUM

PUBLICATIONS (cont'd)

• Maciukenas, J. "Theodor Holm Nelson: Visualizing on-screen interaction through sketching," Presentation at the Computer Science Colloquium on Text, Context & Intertext in the Digital Library: Collaborative Research Opportunities between the Humanities & Computer Science, Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, IL, May 2006.

CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS

- American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) Annual Meeting, San Jose, CA. (2015)
- An Event Apart: Three Days of Design, Code, and Content, Chicago, IL. (2014)
- Chicago Colloquium on Digital Humanities & Computer Science, Chicago, IL. (2012)
- What to do with a Million Books, the Chicago Symposium on Digital Humanities and Computer Science. University of Chicago. (2006)
- Image & Meaning 2.2: A workshop on visualization of scientific information, sponsored by MIT, NSF, and Sigma Xi. Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, IL. (2007)
- Cyberinfrastructure Institute for Humanities, Arts, and Social Sciences. University of California at San Diego. (2006)
- Edward Tufte seminar in presenting data and information. Louisville, KY. (2004)

GRANTS

- Ethics in the details: An NSF project to integrate ethics into the graduate Engineering curriculum. Riley, K. (PI), Davis, M., **Maciukenas, J.** & Cox, A.
- Teaching grant for innovative faculty. Riley, K. (PI) & Maciukenas, J.
- Submitted NSF Digital Humanities Startup Grant proposal for *A project management model for digital library development in smaller, under-resourced Humanities departments.* with Harrington, K., Riley, K. & **Maciukenas, J.** (2007)

SERVICE

- Brand Strategy Working Group, Illinois Institute of Technology. (2017-2018)
- University Web Content Management System Advisory Board, Illinois Institute of Technology. (2012-2016)
- Reviewed manuscript submission "Where theory meets practice: a critical comparison of research into identifying letters and craft knowledge of type design" for *The Design Journal*. (2008)
- Student Marketing Advisory Board, Illinois Institute of Technology. (2006-2007)
- Website Judging Team, IPRO Day, Illinois Institute of Technology. (2005-2006)